Guide to the Virtual Library of Virginia records, 1994-2004
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Virtual Library of Virginia records
1994-2004
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
Virtual Library of Virginia
C0148
10 linear feet (20 boxes)
The collection contains documents and correspondence from the development and operations of the Virtual Library of Virginia (VIVA) consortium from its founding onward. Among the documents included are agendas, minutes, and supporting documents from Committee meetings, articles about VIVA, correspondence, contracts, listservs, meeting minutes, policies and procedures, proposals, publications, reports, and printouts of webpages.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Collection donated by Katherine Perry in 1997-2010.
Historical Information
The Virtual Library of Virginia (VIVA) is a consortium organized in 1994 to provide, in an equitable, cooperative and cost effective manner, enhanced access to library and information resources for Commonwealth of Virginia institutes of higher education serving the higher education community. VIVA facilitates its member libraries cooperative purchase of electronic databases and sharing of other resources such as their valuable print collections.
The 39 State-assisted academic colleges and universities in Virginia are charter members of VIVA by legislative action. These include the 6 public doctoral institutions; 9 comprehensive institutions; and 24 community colleges and two-year branch campuses. In addition, the private non-profit institutions of higher education comprising the Virginia Independent College and University Library Association (VICULA) have participated as charter members from the inception of VIVA. The Library of Virginia, as a State library agency with educational and research mission, also participates as a member of VIVA.
Scope and Content
The collection contains documents and correspondence from the development and operations of the Virtual Library of Virginia (VIVA) consortium from its founding onward as documented by Kathy Perry the Director of VIVA.
Series 1 contains documents generated by VIVA committees. Committees include the Steering Committee, the Resource Users Committee, the Outreach Committee, the Resource Sharing Committee, the task force on Cataloging and Intellectual Access, the User Group, the Special Collections Committee and the Technical Issues Committee. Material includes meeting agendas, minutes and notes, committee assignment information, committee reports, committee lists, budget information, correspondence, journal subscription information, information about specific software and computer programs, cost savings and value added survey information, documents from regional meetings and workshops, lists of institutional participants, contact directories, VIVA information packets, travel reimbursement information, interlibrary loan information, press releases and information about the Virginia Heritage Project.
Series 2 contains material generated by the various meetings, forums, training sessions and workshops. Documents include correspondence, evaluation forms, meeting agendas, notes, and minutes, registration and attendance information, contact lists and directories, logistical information, information about software and computer programs, fact sheets, group lists, information about electronic resources, VIVA packets, VIVA publications, travel reimbursement information and ILL guidelines and lending reports. The series is divided into two subseries, Regional Meetings and Workshops.
Series 3 contains information generated by VIVA contact directories. Material includes VIVA contact directories, committee lists, memos, correspondence, faxes, a personnel directory, notes, maps and lists of participating institutions, VIVA fact sheets, recommendations for organization structure and VIVA publications.
Series 4 contains information generated by the cost saving and value added survey. The CSVA survey was sent to VIVA member institutions "to assess the impact of VIVA's shared purchase of electronic resources". Material includes rough drafts and final versions of the survey, blank and completed surveys, CSVA survey executive summaries, notes, budget information, narrative summaries, questionnaire responses, instructional letters, correspondence, documents on three and a half inch floppy disks, lists of journals available from Ideal (Academic Press), IAC, and Project Muse, survey distribution checklists, lists of VIVA participating institutions, survey results, financial benefit reports, information about the VIVA listserv and home page, VIVA fact sheets, a rough draft of the State Council of Higher Education in Virginia Library Advisory Committee 1998-2000 Biennial Budget Proposal, VIVA electronic resources spreadsheets and subscription prices worksheets.
Series 5 contains miscellaneous documents generated by the Virtual Library of Virginia. Material includes correspondence, travel reimbursement information, information from the Allied Health and Nursing Collaborative Collection Project, VIVA publications, newspaper articles, information about the State Council of Higher Education in Virginia Library Advisory Committee 1998-2000 Biennial Budget Proposal, VIVA website information, vendor client reviews, information about authentication, security, and access management issues for VIVA users, lists of VIVA institutional participants, budget information and lending information.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged according to subject.
Series 1: VIVA Committees, April 1994-September 2004 (Boxes 1-13)
Series 2: VIVA Events and Meetings, January 1995-August 2001 (Boxes 14-16)
Series 3: VIVA Contacts Directories, January 1995-September 2000 (Boxes 17-18)
Series 4: VIVA Cost Saving and Value Added Survey, July 1994-July 1999 (Boxes 19-20)
Series 5: Miscellaneous VIVA Documents, November 1994-January 2003 (Box 20)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds the George Mason University Libraries records.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
VIVA, the Virtual Library of Virginia.
Subjects:
Library cooperation--Virginia.
Contents List
- Series 1: Committees, April 1994-September 2004; (13 boxes)
  This series contains documents generated by VIVA committees. Committees include the Steering Committee, the Resource Users Committee, the Outreach Committee, the Resource Sharing Committee, the task force on Cataloging and Intellectual Access, the User Group, the Special Collections Committee and the Technical Issues Committee. The series is made up of six subseries each containing documents from the primary committees: the Steering Committee, the Resource Users Committee, the Resource Sharing Committee, the Outreach Committee, the Special Collections Committee, and the Technical Issues Committee.
  - Subseries 1.1: VIVA Steering Committee Meetings, July 1994-June 2002
    Material generated before and after monthly VIVA Steering Committee meetings. The Steering Committee meeting files include meeting agendas, minutes and notes, committee assignment information, committee reports, committee lists, budget information, and correspondence in regards to the monthly meetings as well as annual retreats.
    - Steering Committee Minutes, July 29, 1994-September 21, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Minutes of monthly Steering Committee meetings form July of 1994 to September of 1995.
    - Steering Committee Minutes, November 9, 1995-September 18, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Minutes of monthly Steering Committee meetings from November of 1995 to September of 1997.
    - Steering Committee Mtg., July 29, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Agenda, notes, correspondence and minutes from the July 1994 meeting.
    - Steering Committee Mtg., August 17, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Minutes, correspondence and committee member list from the August 1994 meeting at the Institute of Textile Technology in Charlottesville.
    - Steering Committee Mtg., September 15, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Correspondence, notes, minutes and agendas from the September 1994 at Washington and Lee University in Lexington. Also included are a Washington and Lee University campus map and Electronics Collections Committee progress report.
    - Steering Committee Mtg., October 13, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Minutes, correspondence and agenda from the October meeting at James Madison University in Harrisonburg. Also included is information about an upcoming vendor fair and a TRW Smart Search computer program.
    - Vendor Fair, November 8, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Supporting informational publications from Data Research Associates.
    - Vendor Fair, November 8, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Variety of documents related to vendor fair held at Virginia Commonwealth University in Richmond. Attendees lists, logistical information and directions to fair, correspondence, and registration forms.
    - Steering Committee Mtg., November 10, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Minutes, agendas, notes and correspondence from the November meeting at Virginia Commonwealth University in Richmond. Also included is information about the OCLC SiteSearch System, the VIVA website design, vendor fair responses, and an article from The Richmond Times-Dispatch about college budget cuts.
    - Steering Committee Mtg., December 8, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Attendance list, minutes and notes from December meeting at Virginia Commonwealth University in Richmond. Also included is budget information, VIVA stationary, correspondence about SOLINET, an article about VIVA from the Virginia Pilot, and meeting minutes from the User Services Committee.
    - Steering Committee Mtg., January 11, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Agendas, attendance sheets, notes, minutes and correspondence about the January meeting at J. Sargeant Reynolds Community College in Richmond. Also included is a VIVA information packet and meeting minutes from the User Services Committee.
    - Steering Committee Mtg., February 9, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Notes and agendas from the February meeting at Randolph-Macon College in Ashland. Also included is contact list requests, VIVA press release, Ariel literature, miscellaneous correspondence.
    - Steering Committee Mtg., March 8-10, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Notes, minutes and agendas from the March meeting at James Madison University in Harrisonburg. Also included is budget information, committee member lists, and funding information from the Department of Commerce.
    - Steering Committee Retreat, March 8-9, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Agendas for the retreat at James Madison University in Harrisonburg. Also included are Electronic Collections Committee goals and accomplishments and funding information from the Department of Commerce.
    - Steering Committee Mtg., April 13, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Notes, agendas and minutes from the April meeting at the Monroe Building in Richmond. Also included are database factsheets, budget information, and regional meeting attendance lists
    - Steering Committee Mtg., May 11, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Agendas, notes and minutes from May meeting at the University of Virginia in Charlottesville. Also included is budget information, Electronics Collections Committee goals, and committee lists.
    - Steering Committee Mtg., June 8, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Agendas, committee lists and notes from the June meeting at Old Dominion University in Norfolk. Also included is an Interim Report of the Joint Subcommittee Studying the Reorganization of the State Library and Archives, correspondence from the Virginia council of higher learning, information about Ohio Library and Information Network, contact lists,
    - Steering Committee Mtg., July 13, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Notes, committee lists and agendas from the July meeting at Sweet Briar College in Sweet Briar. Also included are VIVA contract samples and budget information.
    - Steering Committee Mtg., September 21-22, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Notes, agendas and action items from the September meeting at George Mason University in Fairfax. Also included are Library Advisory Committee meeting minutes, budget information, and committee lists.
    - Steering Committee Meeting Information (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Documents, articles, minutes, notes and other information for the steering committee meetings.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, November 9, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Agendas, notes, correspondence and minutes from the November meeting in Roanoke. Also included is information about UVA's Library website, Project Muse subscription information, and budget information.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, December 14, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Agendas, correspondence and notes from the December meeting at the College of William and Mary in Williamsburg. Also included is budget information and Library Advisory Committee meeting minutes.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, February 8, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Agendas, correspondence, notes and minutes from the February meeting in Richmond. Also included is First Search budget information and a list of objectives for the CCM.
    - Steering Committee Minutes, March 14, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Agendas, Collection Committee reports, notes, minutes and correspondence from the March meeting at the University of Virginia in Charlottesville. Also included are committee member lists, First Search usage information, budget information, faculty newsletters, Ariel survey, planning retreat agenda, VIVA logo edits, interlibrary loan information, and a report to the Council of Higher Education.
    - Steering Committee Minutes, May 9, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Agendas, minutes and notes from the May meeting at the College of William and Mary in Williamsburg. Also included is Ariel information, interlibrary loan information, cost-savings and value-added survey, first search usage information and questionnaire, budget information, and collections committee recommendations.
    - Spring Retreat, June 13-14, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Outline, questionnaire and notes from the VIVA spring retreat at Radford University. Also included is information from the State Council of Higher Education in Virginia Library Advisory Committee meeting.
    - Spring Retreat, June 13-14, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      VIVA Travel and Training costs summary and information, presentation slide notes, correspondence, keynote address notes, and minutes from the VIVA spring retreat at Radford University.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, August 1, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Agendas, correspondence, minutes, action items and notes from the August meeting at the Virginia Commonwealth University in Richmond. Also included is a recommendation to establish a cataloging committee, VIVA publicity plan and budget information.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, September 26, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Agendas, notes and action items from the September meeting at Mary Washington College in Fredericksburg. Also included is budget information, User Services committee meeting minutes, VIVA mission statement and vision information, contact lists, JMU ROCCO Forum publication, presentation slides about the cooperative collection development,
    - Steering Committee Meeting, November 8, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Agendas, correspondence, action items and notes from the November meeting at the University of Virginia in Charlottesville. Also included are lists of participating institutions, presentation slides about VIVA, and CCM workshop planning correspondence.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, December 5-6, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Agendas, correspondence, minutes, action items and notes from the December meeting at Virginia State University in Petersburg. Also included is State Council of Higher Education in Virginia Library Advisory Committee meeting minutes and information, VIVA fact sheets, budget information, organizational structure recommendations, a press release, restructuring information.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, January 30, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Agendas, correspondence, notes and minutes from the January meeting. Also included is information about the use of virtual meetings and organizational structure recommendations.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, March 6, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Agendas, correspondence, action items and notes from the March meeting at the Library of Virginia in Richmond. Also included is a JSTOR proposal, organizational structure recommendations, budget information, committee lists and collections committee meeting minutes.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, May 12, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Agendas, action items, notes, and minutes from the May meeting at Mary Washington College in Fredericksburg. Also included is a First Search renewal and OVID proposition, interlibrary loan guidelines and budget information.
    - Spring Retreat, May 12-13, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Agendas, correspondence, attendance sheets and notes from the Spring retreat at Mary Washington College in Fredericksburg. Also included are presentation slides about VIVA's accomplishments, committee and contact lists, cost savings and value added survey executive summary, budget information and a VIVA pamphlet.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, June 5, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      Agendas, correspondence, minutes, action items and notes from the June meeting at Christopher Newport University in Newport News. Also included is a First Search renewal and OVID proposition, institutional cost sharing options, budget information, cataloging guidelines, User Services committee meeting minutes, VIVA participating institutions, Senate resolution no. 218 regarding the demand for technologically skilled workers in Virginia industry, committee lists, Library Advisory Committee meeting minutes and a VIVA information packet.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, July 17, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Agendas, minutes and notes from the July meeting at the James Monroe Building in Richmond. Also included is a draft proposal to the State Council on Higher Education for Virginia and VIVA Publicity Committee information.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, September 18-19, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      Agendas, correspondence and notes from the September meeting at the Virginia Military Institute in Lexington. Also included is a Library Materials Funding Study and budget information.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, November 6, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Agendas, notes and correspondence from the November meeting at the University of Virginia in Charlottesville. Also included is information from the Consortium of Consortia meeting, listserv and home page information, cost savings and value added survey information, budget information, VIVA information packet and committee lists.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, December 4-5, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Agendas, correspondence and notes from the December meeting at Blue Ridge Community College in Weyers Cave. Also included is collections budget information, committee information and State Council of Higher Education for Virginia executive summary.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, January 16, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      Agendas, notes and correspondence from the January meeting at Virginia Commonwealth University in Richmond. Also included is a 1997 House of Delegates standing committee list, a list of Virginia state legislators, Richmond Times-Dispatch articles and budget information.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, March 11, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Agendas, notes and correspondence from the March meeting at the University of Richmond in Richmond. Also included is a steering committee list, funding information, journal information, Association of College and Research Libraries publication, VIVA electronic resources use statistics, Congressional Informational Service information, selection of electronic information document from the International Coalition of Library Consortia and Library Advisory Committee meeting minutes.
    - Steering Committee Retreat, May 5-6, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      Agendas, correspondence and notes from the May retreat at the University of Virginia in Charlottesville. Also included is budget information and presentation transparencies about the biennial budget.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, June 4, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      Agendas, correspondence, minutes and notes from the June meeting at Old Dominion University in Norfolk. Also included is a User Services Committee report, a Steering Committee report from the May 1998 retreat, budget information, cataloging guidelines and Library Advisory Committee meeting materials.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, August 14, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      Minutes, correspondence and notes from the August meeting conducted via conference call.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, September 24-25, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      Agendas, correspondence, minutes and notes from the September meeting at Virginia Tech in Blacksburg. Also included is a Collections Committee report, archival repository survey, committee lists, electronic resource allocation spreadsheet, State Committee on Higher Education for Virginia Library Advisory Committee information.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, November 2, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      Minutes, notes and correspondence from the November meeting conducted via conference call. Also included is information about Mid-Atlantic Crossroads and Project Muse usage information.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, December 3-4, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      Agendas, action items, minutes, correspondence and notes from the December meeting at the College of William and Mary in Williamsburg. Also included is budget information, VIVA presentation slides, definition of VIVA associate membership, committee lists, VIVA organizational charts,
    - Steering Committee Meeting, March 11-12, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      Agendas, correspondence, notes and minutes from the March meeting at Longwood College in Farmville. Also included is a collections committee report, library services guidelines, electronic resources usage statistics and State Committee on Higher Education for Virginia Library Advisory Committee information.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, June 3-4, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Agendas, correspondence and notes from the June meeting at Clinch Valley College in Wise. Also included is an information management, presentation slides and paper, collections committee meeting minutes and budget information. Large documents William B Allen remarks "The Library is the Center of Learning", 1999 Virginia Plan for Higher Education, Virginia Higher Education Performance Model and Inflation Measures for Schools Colleges and Libraries.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, July 9, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Agendas, notes, minutes and correspondence from the July meeting at the University of Virginia in Charlottesville. Also included is a list of committee assignments and committee lists.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, September 28, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      Correspondence, votes, and minutes, from the September meeting which was an electronic vote.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, October 8, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 5)
      Agendas, notes and correspondence from the October meeting at the James Monroe Building in Richmond. Also included are committee lists, participant lists and articles from the Chronicle of Higher Education Almanac.
    - Steering Committee Meeting, December 2-3, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 6)